Welcome to lecture 11.
Good afternoon everyone.
So we're going to continue what we have started last week in designing a process of micro
architecture.
Remember that we started with single cycle data pass and designing also the control logic for that.
We discussed a lot that single cycle essentially is not a good way to go because of the fact that we
need to wait.
Essentially we need to design the database data pass that can handle the longest instruction and all
other instruction.
They also need to wait for the longest instruction.
But essentially it was a good practice, you know, as a instruction to learn how to design this data
pass.
Today we're going to quickly continue our wrap up what we have left off last week and then we're
going to get to multi cycle, multi cycle processor design and hopefully we get to also to pipelined
processor design.
So we actually have a kind of ambitious plan for today and let's see how much we can cover
hopefully.
OK.
So yeah, this is the agenda that we had for kind of last week and today and also tomorrow we're
going to get to hopefully by the to the end of issues in pipelining by tomorrow.
And then next week we're going to get to more in the line of out of order execution hopefully.
OK.
And here are also some readings for multi cycle.
Actually we're going to use a lot from Harris and Harris Chapter 7.4, which actually did a good job.
And we also, I'm going to mention some part of the lecture which is from the pattern, pattern
appendices.
So you can also check that if you're more interested.
And then hopefully tomorrow, today and tomorrow, we're going to also get to pipelining and
pipelining issues.
OK, So this is a single cycle micro architecture that we have built last week.
And just to jog your memory.
And essentially we were analysing the performance of it.
We discussed about, you know, as a toy example, we consider different latencies for different part
of the data pass.
And essentially we discussed that all different instruction, what are the stages in the, in the
architecture that they they need to go through.
So load word instruction is actually the longest instruction that needs to go over all these steps.
And that accounts for the longest delay where there are some instructions like jump instruction,
which is actually quite fast.
But in single cycle architecture, basically we don't have any other choice.
So all the instruction they need to wait for 600 microsecond in this picosecond for this example.
For example, we also discussed through the end of the lecture about the control logic, that control
logic might not be on the critical path more or less, but it can be also the case when we have a
lot of instructions that we want to support.
Control logic can be also very much complex as we also going to see more in out of order execution.
Control logic can be actually very, very complex which can actually cause also longer latency for
us.
OK yeah, essentially this was the part that we we basically left.
So what is the really the slowest instruction to process?
And essentially the in real world memory is slow, not magic.
Remember that we consider, we assume that memory can be accessed by one cycle, which in the
beginning I said that this is not a good assumption to make.
But for simplicity we can consider that.
But in real world actually memory is very slow.
And some of these instructions they need actually multiple memory accesses.
So all instruction, they need at least one memory access because of the fetch operation.
But some instruction might have two memory accesses.
And if your memory is actually quite as slow, which is kind of the case, which can be actually like
100 of nanoseconds to access your memory, then you're going to have a double latency, for example,
for some of your instructions.
So in the end, essentially the question is that does it make sense to have a simple register to
register at or jump to take 150 nanosecond plus all there to perform a memory operation?
So this, for example, is the assumption that memory takes 150 nanosecond.
And basically what if you need to access memory more than once to process an instruction.
So all instruction they need at least one memory access for the fetch.
But for load load instruction we also need to access memory for load.
You can also think of some.
More complex instructions that essentially you access a memory and you read the data and that data
is actually a pointer which you might want to use that pointer to access another location in the
memory.
So there can be actually one instruction that you might have 3 memory accesses for example.
So it can be actually much more longer in the end.
So yeah, so that's why For these reasons, actually single cycle micro architecture is not a good
design to go.
And here actually I'm also going to quickly recap the problems that we have in single cycle micro
architecture.
So basically it's contrived that all instructions run and as slow as the slowest instruction.
And it's actually very inefficient because all instructions run as slow as the slowest instruction.
And it should also must provide worst case combinational resources in parallel as required by any
instructions.
So in single cycle, like if there are multiple units that one instruction need to go through it, you
cannot reuse your essentially your your combinational circuits.
So you need to have them in parallel such that you can access them in a combinational way.
So that's actually one of the big weaknesses of this design and which that needs to replicate
essentially a resource if it is needed more than once by an instruction during different parts of
the instruction processing cycle.
Also a single cycle is not necessarily the simplest way to implement an ISA.
There can be tough some complex instruction that design can be actually close to impossible if you
want to for example, support let's say matrix matrix multiplication or for example, if you want to
do let's say string copy or some indexing in a three-dimensional array.
So some of these instructions that actually today's architecture are supporting them, It's almost
impossible to support them in a single cycle architecture because you need to add a lot of
resources, which very quickly is going to be impractical.
And of course, it's not easy to optimise and improve performance because we don't really have a
degree of freedom in single cycle architecture to improve the performance.
OK, so remember, so here I want to discuss about micro architecture design principles.
And I'm going to define these three principles and then we can discuss how the single cycle micro
architecture works.
Regard them.
So one of the for in order to improve performance, you basically it's good to follow these
principles in designing micro architecture.
One of them is critical pass design, which means that we need to find and decrease the maximum
combinational logic delay and then we can break a pass into multiple cycles if it takes too long.
So in in single cycle market architecture, by definition you can try to decrease the maximum
combinational logic delay as a worst case latency, but then you don't really have this freedom to
break into multiple cycles because by definition you have only one cycle to process.
So essentially single cycle micro architecture is not very good at critical pass design principle.
Another important principle is bread and butter or common case design that we essentially we want to
optimise for, for the operation, which is more common, spend time and resources on where it makes
sense, where it matters most.
So in single cycle, essentially we don't really do anything regardless, even if one instruction
which is very, very slow is happening, just one out of millions of instructions, we need to support
that and all other instruction they need to wait for that longest instruction.
So essentially micro single cycle micro architecture is very bad at this principal design, which is
essentially common case versus uncommon case.
So in single cycle micro architecture, we cannot really do much about it.
And another one is also balanced design, which is balanced instruction and data flow through
hardware components and to design essentially designed to eliminate bottlenecks, balance the
hardware for the work.
However, in single cycle micro architecture, we cannot really do that also because we need to
duplicate or replicate a lot of resources just to make sure that we can essentially execute
instruction in a combinational way.
Remember that for example, we need to for example, we can, we need to we have two memories
essentially.
So for fetching instruction, we we can access, we access the memory which is instruction memory to
fetch instruction.
And also when we want to fetch or write or read or load data to the memory, we have a different
memory which is data memory.
So you cannot really have for example 1 memory to handle both instruction and and data accesses.
So essentially.
Single cycle market market architecture is breaking all these principles and that's why not actually
people that they really want to design a good system, they are not following that principle.
They are not following this kind of single cycle design.
So I kind of did that, but you can also think about some other reasons that single cycle micro
architecture is not very good at these principles.
OK, here also a kind of side about system design principles that essentially I think you have seen
it in some of the earliest lectures in this course.
But essentially when designing computer systems or architecture, it is important to follow good
principles.
And this is actually true for any system design, which can be also the case for real architectures,
building bridges, training stations and also many others things that you can think of.
And yeah, and also there is this famous architect that says that architecture should be based open
principle and not open precedent.
And remember about this design, I don't know if you have seen it in this course or is this the first
time?
So it's kind of a building in a in a nice forest, but this looks actually designed based on
precedent actually, but more principal design can be something like that.
You know that you design.
Do you know what the name of this building is anyone?
Yes, yes, yeah, yeah.
So, yeah.
So it's actually close to somewhere close to also Pittsburgh, which professor Muto was there for
ASPLOS conference and also he was teaching in Pittsburgh in the past.
He was teaching and also professor in Carnegie Mellon University.
So this actually design looks very much in the line of principles.
I'm not going into detail of that, but it's actually like a very organic design architecture, which
you can also read it if you're interested.
So if you compare this and that, basically you can feel about designing open principle or open
precedent essentially.
OK, so yeah, so I'm not going to spend more time on this.
We already discussed, but essentially in this course we will continue to cover key principles and
here also some differences where you can learn more.
I'm going to show something about for the first one, but you can also check other papers if you're
interested in future.
So a key system design principle if I if I want to summarise a lot, is that we should keep it simple
and seeing a cycle.
Micro architecture is not simple, especially when you think about complex instructions, how you
really want to support them is not really simple.
And there is a nice quote that says that everything should be made as simple as possible but no
simpler.
Anyone knows from who this quote is?
Yes.
No.
OK, it's kind of a bit paraphrased, but it's actually from Einstein.
And there is also another basically important principle which is we need to keep it low cost.
And there is also another quote from someone says that an engineer or designer is a person who can
do for a dime what any fool can do for a dollar, essentially like $0.10 and $1.00.
So in the end, simplicity and also low cost, these two are very important when we want to design
micro architecture.
So for more, you can actually also check this writing from Butler Lampson hints for computer system
design, which actually also has a more, let's say updated version in 2021.
So you can access it from this archive if you're interested.
OK, but now we can get to our favorite question.
Can we do better?
Any question from single cycle micro architecture?
Very good.
So we want to get to multi cycle micro architectures and the goal is to let each instruction take
close to only as much as it really needs.
So the idea is that we want to determine clock cycle time independently of instruction processing
time.
In single cycle micro architecture we always need to consider the longest instruction and then the
clock cycle is dependent based on that.
But here in multi cycle is actually independent.
You can think of OK, I want to have a clock cycle time of let's.
Say 1 nanosecond and then you need to make sure that you break execution of instruction in enough
number of stage such that you can accommodate each stage in one one nanosecond essentially.
So that's that's the idea here.
So each instruction takes as many clock cycle as it needs to take and the multiple state transitions
for instruction and the states followed by each instruction is different essentially.
So the idea is that hopefully some instructions like load, they're going to take a lot of states,
but some instructions like jump addition, these are going to take much lower number of fewer number
of states.
And in the end, hopefully your average CPI is actually low.
So also to jog your memory, you remember about this slide.
So essentially we already covered the choice one which is the single cycle micro architecture.
Now we want to get to the choice.
The second choice which we architectural estate is going to break to is going to transition to
architectural estate plus micro architectural estate.
And then that is going to also get to another micro architectural estate and another.
And then in the end we're going to get to the final architectural estate which is visible to the
programmer.
So essentially programmer cannot see all these in between micro architectural estates that we have.
Yeah.
And these are actually you are already aware of that, that we can have multiple steps in between in
order to transition from architectural state to another architectural state.
And this also I think you remember that we build this for LC3 micro architecture kind of FSM that we
went over it.
And here also you remember that this was was the fetch phase that we have this finite state machine
and then the code phase and depending depending on the OP code and what we want to do, essentially
your FSM is branching through different lines of states.
And yeah, so in today in this lecture, we're going to also be something similar, but it bit more
detail for like complete data pass and also hopefully the control design.
OK.
And these are also you've seen that in the past also.
So just I think just to be for some quick summary of multi cycle, the high level idea.
So it provides a lot of benefits, remember about our principle design.
So in critical pass design, actually it provides the fact that we can reduce the critical pass
independently of the worst case processing time of any instruction.
So that's the way that we can optimise for the critical pass design and also bread and butter.
Of course, multi cycle can help with that because you can optimise the number of states it takes to
execute important instructions that make up much of the execution time.
Like for example, you're you, you profile your application and you're going to see that 90% of the
instructions is just addition and multiplication, right?
Then you can actually optimise your data pass and control unit for addition and multiplication,
which can help you get better performance overall for those applications.
And also in balanced design, essentially no need to provide more capability or resources that really
needed.
We're going to see that how we can reuse our our computational unit or also other logics in the in
the in the data pass to do different things essentially.
OK.
But of course, I mean multi cycle design also have some downsides.
One of them is that we need to store the intermediate result at the end of each clock cycle.
So remember that from architectural estate we go to some architectural estate plus some micro, micro
architectural estate so that you need to store and then from that to another micro architectural
estate you need to store.
So there are some steps in between that you need to store and that essentially you need to add
memory logics like you need to add latches registers in the data pass, which will add complexity.
And also remember this register set up and hold overhead like sequencing overhead that we talked
about it in the our timing lecture.
So that is going to be paid multiple times for an instruction.
Another issue is that we have a limited concurrency in multi cycle design.
This can, can be, it's going to be much more clear when we get to the pipeline design because we're
going to start with this problem limited concurrency to motivate our the pipeline processor design.
But just to understand it, limited concurrency is coming from the fact that only a small part of the
machine you use at any point in time.
So a multi cycle when you're basically when you're fetching instructions, there are a lot of other
parts of the data pass that they are kind of ideal and they're not doing anything so you can think
of.
Now we can benefit from that for better concurrency and better performance, but we're going to get
to that hopefully today when we are discussing pipeline processor design.
OK, so here also I want to show that essentially multi cycle here in LC3 data pass we we had to add
some register like instruction register, memory address register, memory data register.
And these are the register that essentially you add when you have a multi cycle data pass.
In single cycle database, we didn't have any of these registers, right?
We had only this register file which is considered as a state register and everything else was just
combinational logic, right.
But in essentially in the multi cycle design you need to add these registers.
And here also remember about this performance analysis that we said that in multi cycle we have two
degrees of freedom to optimise independently.
So we can play with the CPI and also clock cycle time, which is good to improve performance.
But we now we can get to the closer look how we can design multi cycle.
Any question?
OK, so if you're interested, you can I recommend you check this writing from this paper from from
Maurice Wilks, the best way to design an automatic calculating machine.
It's very actually inspiring.
I recommend everyone to read that.
And we're going to also get some part of this lecture and the concept of micro coded and micro
program machines that I don't want to talk about it right now, but we're going to get to that.
OK.
So the key idea here is that one can implement the process instruction step as a final state machine
that sequences between the States and eventually returns back to the fetch instruction state.
So think about FSM that we discussed in the past.
So here a state is defined by the control signals asserted in it and the control signals for the
next state are determining the current state.
So essentially in the, the control logic is going to be a finite state machine that in each state
you set some control signals which going to be used for the next state essentially because we want
to hide latencies.
If if you generate control signals that you need for this state for the current state in the in the
same state, then there's going to actually end links your critical pass latency because these
control signal needs to be generated.
And then you can do computation which are going to add your critical pass latency.
Whereas if you generate control signals that you need one cycle earlier, which we're going to do
here, then actually you don't, you don't increase your critical pass latency for that reason.
OK, so a basic multi cycle architecture, we devise the instruction processing cycle into States and
a multi cycle micro architecture sequences from a state to a state to process and instruction.
And also the behaviour of the entire processor is specified fully by a finite state machine and also
in a state which is a clock cycle control.
Signals control two things.
One of them is how the data pass should process the data and how to generate the control signals for
the next clock cycle, which we're going to also use that.
OK, so we're going to basically design this multi cycle micro architecture.
Remember this single cycle micro architecture from your book Harris and Harris Chapter 7.3, We're
going to also do that for multi cycle.
We're going to also actually follow your book for that.
I don't want to repeat again.
Why do we want multi cycle?
Essentially by now I think we all know that a multi cycle is a better architecture micro
architecture compared to single cycle.
But in single cycle we have low clock frequency and high hardware cost.
In multi cycle we have better clock frequency.
Simpler instructions also take only a few clock cycles which kind of better and bother and we can
reuse expensive hardware across multiple cycle which is more or less a better balanced design.
But there are also some weaknesses that we have discussed about it.
OK, so we can think of what are the optimization that we want to make when we want to when we have a
multi cycle design data pass.
One of them is that in single cycle we have two memories, one for memory storage instruction and one
for data.
So here we can actually have only use a single memory which provides lower cost for us.
We're going to see how, but it's possible also in single cycle market market micro architecture we
need three others.
So essentially we need.
Adders in ALU.
We also need adders for for program counter when we want to do +4 and also we need adders when we
want to calculate the branch target address.
But here for example we we want to use only one ALU for all operations which can be much lower cost.
Also, single cycle micro architecture, each instruction takes only one cycle, but here we want to
essentially determine clock cycle time independently of instruction processing time and divide
instruction into multiple clock cycles, which we already discussed about.
OK, so we're going to start with this instruction load word in our multi cycle pipeline and then see
how we want to implement it.
Remember that we're going to do the same as we did in single cycle micro architecture that we start
with the data pass and then we see how we we need to add the components in order to support all
different instructions like the instruction that we consider.
And then we design the control logic here also is not is completely the same.
It's not magic.
So we start with the with data pass and for different instruction, we go over different units that
we need to add.
And then after that, we're going to get to the essentially the control logic.
So this instruction load word, I'm not going over the semantic of it.
I think you by now you know it, But essentially we add this register to this number to this offset
to calculate the memory access address.
And for that region of the memory, you fetch a word which is 4 bytes of data and then you store it
in this register which here is dollar T 0.
So and it's actually load word is the I type instruction.
And here is the formatting of this instruction.
OK, so the first step is how we want to fetch instruction.
We are we're doing it actually for load word.
But essentially the fetch pipe fetch hardware is going to be the same for other instructions as
well.
So, so this is your program counter and this provides the PC address and you access this memory
which now we call it actually instruction data memory because it can be used for both instruction
and data.
And we essentially we read from this memory, we read instruction and here we added a Register here
which is considered as instruction register.
For example, you need to enable this this register and then you store the instruction that you're
reading to this register and then you have this instruction is stored in your instruction register.
Then you're going to use that.
You need this register for multiple reasons.
One of that is that you want to make sure that your instruction is not changed while you are doing
the executing of this instruction because one instruction is going to be executed in multiple
cycles.
So it's important that we have it saved somewhere to make sure that it's not going to be changed.
Also, this memory can be used for other use cases.
So you need to be careful that you're you're not latching data in your instruction memory.
So there should be some Register here that you can handle, enable it or disable it to make sure that
you're really latching instructions.
So we loaded this instruction and and that's essentially the the fetch pipeline.
Then we get to the decoder step, which is very similar to what we've been doing in a single cycle
micro architecture.
So essentially the instruction that we we loaded beats 25 to 21 is going to be the source, the
source address.
So we need to fed them to the register file and then the output of the register file which is a read
data one, we're going to latch it in another register which give you this this register that you
read from your register file.
Also in parallel, you basically input instruction 0 to to 15 as immediate to the to your sign extent
logic.
You do this sign extending and then for the in the next cycle you can do the calculation like the
addition in your ALU that the output, this register that you latched in the previous cycle is going
to be input to your ALU.
And this sign extended also is going to be input to your ALU as the as the second operand.
And you need to control the ALU operation which for example here we want to do addition and the
output of ALU is going to be again latched here.
Makes sense.
OK.
And then you use this output.
This, this is what we are doing here, which is different from a single cycle market micro micro
architecture because now we have 1 memory which is used for instruction and data memory.
So the output of this register is going to be fed to this multiplexer, which in the end essentially
the address that you want to generate to access this instruction and data memory can be defined by
program counter or the output of ALU at least from now.
And that can be basically help us to.
So we add this multiplexer in order to control that.
So for load word instruction, we control, we need to we add this multiplexer and we control this
multiplexer such that this line is going to be fit to the to the address of this memory.
And then we read from the memory and then we need to latch it as a data kind of a memory data
register.
So we latch it here in a in a different register essentially.
And then again, so this going to be this register memory data register is going to be is going to
fit again to the register file because we want to do this right back operation.
So we as a right data to register file and the address for the right register, which is RT is going
to be actually coming from the instruction that haven't changed at all from from the moment that we
fetch.
So it's going to be instruction 20 to to 16.
So we provide that essentially address and we also apply this Reg write, which is the right enable
of the register file in order to make sure that we write this finish this write back operation.
So that's load word execution.
But we also need to do for increment PC because essentially that also important to have in your in
your micro architecture.
So PC +4.
What we can do here is actually we can reuse our ALU for PC +4.
So the PC which is so coming from here, right?
The the current PC, we need to do PC +4.
So the current PC is coming through this through this line.
And then here we add another multiplexer that we, when we want to do PC +4, we essentially select
the current PC instead of output of this register file.
So we select this the current PC.
And then for the second Oprah and we have another multiplexer.
We're going to use other inputs for later slides you're going to see, but one of the input is going
to be 4, which for this instruction for this PC increment, essentially we select of this line which
is 4 and PC is going to be added by 4.
And the output, the here ALU result is going to be used in order to store in this register.
OK.
And now you know why is important also to have this essentially it's important to have this Register
here as an instruction register because so this your PC actually is going to be incremented for the
next cycle which in the end when we access the instruction memory, we're going to actually fetch
another instruction.
But we make sure that this the right enable of this instruction register is disabled such that we
don't latch the next instruction while we are executing the current instruction question.
OK.
For the store word, we need to essentially write data in the this temporary register RT to memory.
So what we do here is that.
Let me see.
Yeah.
So again we need to, so we need to provide two sources you set here for a store board to the
register file.
So essentially we add also this line to to another report of the register file which is the
instruction 20 to 16.
And then also we need to provide latch.
So essentially we can latch both output of the register file and this output is going to be used
because this is the this is the data that you want to store in the memory, right?
So this output of this register is going to be fed as the right data to the memory.
But also you need you need the pipeline to generate the address for the memory.
But that can be handled for the sorry, you need the micro architecture sometimes said my pipeline
because I used to say pipeline because most, I mean all the modern processor pipeline.
So that's why.
Sometimes it's a pipeline, but yeah, so in your micro architecture, you need, you already have the
support in order to generate the address of the memory which we've seen in load word instruction.
So that part is not changed.
So you still need to go from this register.
You read it, you read it and then you add it with the sign extend immediate in the Lu and then
provide the address, you latch it to this register and then provide the address to the memory.
So that also needs to be done.
So that's that's a part of the execution of this instruction store word, which you need to control
it through your FSM design.
But the data that you want to write to your memory, you can actually do it through this.
Essentially this addition added pipe, added micro architecture here in your hardware that you read
from your register file and then you write it to the memory question.
OK, so in the end you need to design basically you need to design have a control logic in FSM such
that control the execution.
But so data paths should should provide enough possibility to essentially to execute all these
instruction.
But as long as you design your your control logic correctly, you should be able to support store
word and load word in this architecture for example.
So for our type instruction also there is not much a lot different.
So here is one of the difference.
For example that which you have seen it also in single cycle micro architecture like the destination
register in our type is actually coming from the instruction 15 to 11 whereas in I type is
instruction 20 to 60.
So there should be a multiplexer here that you can basically select The Reg desk.
And also, yeah, the AAU input is actually coming from the the output of these two registers, right?
So you read from this register file and one of them is going to be the one of the Opran for the ALU.
Another one also is should be selected.
So that multiplexer that we added before here is going to be used again for for the second OPRAN.
So you you draw this line and you need to control this, the ALU source B.
And then in ALU you basically based on the function code, you do the operation and the ALU results.
Yeah, exactly a result.
You latch it here and then you provide it to this multiplexer in order to provide the right data to
the register file.
OK.
Yeah, it's not that's really hard.
Just we need to add this register and also multiplexer.
There should be enough hardware to handle all these instructions.
But then it's the matter of sequencing this hardware like how we manage the order of this hardware
in order to make sure that we execute these instructions.
So branch if equal is also interesting.
I'm going to discuss it now quickly.
So in branch if you call you need to essentially do multiple things.
One of them is actually checking if they if we need to do the branch, right.
So for that you essentially need to read these two registers from the register file.
So this part is going to be the same.
And then in the ALU you will do the for example, the subtract operation.
And if the result of the ALU is 0 this, then it's going to this zero signal is going to be asserted.
So if the if you have zero and then the instruction is branch, then you essentially have this
basically the fact that you want to take the branch and for that you can use to generate the PC
enable signal to update the PC.
So how we generate the target address in the for the B branch E free call for the for the target
address.
Also, we essentially this the immediate is going to be sign extended.
And then we need to do this shifting by two.
So we do this shifting and we input it again to this multiplexer, right?
And yeah, and also the the out another output is actually coming from this here from the from the PC
which coming here.
And this is important to consider that this this PC that now I'm inputting here to this area is
actually already PC Plus 4.
Because once we do the.
We also do the process of PC +4.
So this PC for the for the cycle that I want to do this addition is actually already PC +4.
So PC Plus 4 is going to be input this multiplexer and then comes to this ALU going to be added with
this sign extended shifted by two immediate and and then you generate the results.
And for that you can actually, yeah, input it essentially to the to the PC.
OK.
So yeah, if you put all of them together, you're going to get to this complete multi cycle
processor, this data pass.
You can also check your book Harris and Harris Chapter 7.4 for more, you know, maybe for better
understanding if you want.
But essentially the the overall analysis is the same.
OK, So what is clear here is that we need to add extra registers and these registers are not needed
in single cycle design.
But here we need to add them.
But that brings us some basically efficiency like we have only one ALU and other we also have only
one memory, which is good.
But we now we need to construct the multi cycle control logic.
But any question before that?
No, no two registers.
Yeah.
So I I'm not sure if we have this.
So BEQ is always is something like branch.
If you call and then you put two register like beq dollar S $0.00 S 1 and then a label which is a a
branch target.
So you need to subtract these two registers to to see if they are equal or not.
And then afterwards we'll get the new address to which dual branch, Yes, but no, for that you need
to basically calculate it using your immediate address, which is a same time.
No, no, no, It's actually handling in a different state in the FSN.
We're going to see that, but it's going to be so in in someone cycle, actually you generate the
target address.
I think in the beginning, you're going to generate the target address, which is going to be PC Plus
4 coming from here.
And also the sign extended shifted by two to this multiplexer.
And then you do this addition.
So that's the target address.
But then in the in the next cycle also you calculate if you need to do if you need to take the
branch or not and then reset.
Yes, you also first check if the branch will be taken and only then calculate the target address.
You can also do that.
Yes, instructions can take different amount of time depending on the state of the system.
Yeah, exactly.
So essentially you can do vice versa.
You can actually first resolve if you're going to take the branch and if you want to take the
branch, then you calculate the target address.
You can also do the other way around, which your book is doing the other way around, like
calculating the target address and then see if you want to take the branch or not.
Was that your question or?
Yes.
So instructions even can take different amounts of size.
Oh, that's true.
Yes, of course, of course, of course.
And actually this multiplexer here that we added, I forgot actually to explain this multiplexer is,
is for the fact that whether or not we want to take the branch because so with this ALU, so in the
first, in the very, very early first cycle in the fetch, we calculate PC +4, OK, We calculate PC +4
and we latch it.
So we have PC Plus four in this essentially in this register.
And then in the next cycle, we calculate PC Plus 4 + extended immediate shifted by two.
And then we have it here essentially.
OK.
And then based on that, we decide based on this calculation also we can decide whether or not we
want to take which one.
If we take the zero part, it's going to be like meaning that we're going to take the branch.
The one is going to means that we don't want to take the branch.
Makes sense.
Yes.
Yeah, exactly.
So this should be handled by the control logic.
Yeah, yeah.
It's a matter of how we handle the controllers, yeah.
So I should thank actually this question now because now we get to the nice, you know, clean part
that we take the break and we can after the break we can start designing the control logic.
Let's get back at when the ring bells again.
3:15 and we continue.
OK, let's continue.
So before the break, we constructed the data pass for multi cycle design and now we want to see how
we can control that data pass.
And by now you know that this controller is going to be like similar to what you have learnt from
finance state machine.
So essentially we're going to design this FSF.
So our control unit is going to be is going to generate a lot of signals.
Some of them are going to be used as a multiplexer selectors.
Some of them are going to be used as register enables to basically control whether or not we are
allowed to load or not.
And also going to use to generate this the control of the ALU what operation you're going to do.
OK, so we start with the fetch.
So the first state, essentially you have a reset that whenever you reset your control, you're
starting from the fetch state.
And from this state, essentially you need to you have these output for the for the control signals,
like for example this multiplexer, you need to put 0 as a selector.
Essentially you use the PC value as the address for this memory.
So this is going to be 0 and also this mem write needs to be also zero because you don't want to
write to the memory.
Again.
We have this principle that we don't want to harm.
So for those components that we don't want to do anything, especially the storage components, we are
OK with reading from them but we make sure that we don't change the values in those storage.
So we, we always need to make sure that we provide zero to the right enable and then we read from
this memory and this also this register for the instruction memory for the instruction register,
the right enable needs to be 1.
So that's why this instruction right is activated here.
Also we the PC source needs to be 0.
Essentially we calculate the ALU, the PC +4 from this.
Yeah, exactly.
PC Plus 4 is going to be selected and then it's going to be fit to this Register here.
Also the the the PC the enable, the right enable should be 1 because you want to also latch PC Plus
four in the next cycle.
Yeah, so I went over some of these operation.
Also in ALU you need to do addition because you want to do PC +4.
So that's why here we need to select the current PC.
So this multiplexer, for example, needs to be 0, which is a LUSRASRCA, right?
So we put 0 for that.
And then also for the second source of the ARU we need to fit 4 value.
So that's why for the second one, we provide 01 and ALU needs to do addition.
So the code for addition is 010 for example.
And then that's provides the for the the logic to do the addition for the ALU.
So that's more or less the thing.
So for fetch, we essentially have this state that we need to control all these control signals.
And in the next cycle, essentially when we get to this, essentially at the rising edge of the clock,
PC Plus 4 is going to be latched in this program counter.
And also instruction that you have read from the memory is going to be latched in this instruction
register, OK.
And now we need to get to this the code stage.
So in the code stage, essentially your book consider that it's actually state is completely empty
because essentially we don't need to control anything.
So we always read, we always read from the register file and the read addresses from the register
file is actually always similar.
So we read from the register file and these registers which which are the output of the register
file, they always latch.
So we always from the from the register file and we always latch the output.
So there is no, let's say right enable for this register.
And since the register, the instruction register is not changing while we are executing the
instruction, essentially the output of this register is going to be also fixed.
There is no change in that as so your book essentially consider that decoder stage is completely
empty.
It can be different if you change your data pass essentially, but but here in this case, you don't
need to do anything.
And then so you can actually also share states.
You don't need to add for each instruction, you don't need to add different states.
So all the instructions actually need to go through this fetch and decode.
But then after that, you can think of, OK, I'm going to branch over load of states that can be
different from different instructions.
However, some of these instructions, they are still sharing the same sequence more or less.
So you can also share the states in order to reduce the complexity of your control logic.
So for example, here we say that after the decode, if the opcode is load word or a store word, we're
going to get to this, the second state, which is a memory address.
So in this state, essentially we need to generate the address that we want to access the memory and
that address can be used to write to the memory or read from the memory.
And then for the load word.
So after that if your instruction is load word, you need to essentially add another state to control
this instruction or data.
Essentially this multiplexer here.
So remember that we added this multiplexer here in order to make sure that the in order to control
that the address that we want to access the memory is coming from the PC or coming from the coming
from the ALU result, which is the address.
So this instruction or data, yeah, it's going to here, it's going to select this line 1.
And then also so we read from the memory and this data needs to be written also in the register
file.
So for the for the next state, you need to apply these values as well.
Like the control logic needs to provide Regdis need to set regdis to 0, which is yeah, this one
Regdis here needs to be 0 because it's actually a load word instructions I type.
So I type the the memo, the register, the destination register address is actually coming from 16 to
21 part of the instruction.
So that's why 16 to 20, sorry, part of the instruction.
So that's why we are selecting this line.
And then also mem to rate should be 1 because we want to read, we are loading from the memory to the
register file.
And rewrite also needs to be asserted because we want to write to the register file and then we can
finish the load, load word instruction in essentially 5 cycles, OK.
And similarly, if your instruction is store word after state two, you're going to get to another
state which you need to handle the right writing that data that you read from the register file to
the memory.
So you need to apply memwrite essentially such that you write to the memory.
So that's for restore word for our type after the code you essentially you can think of you know how
to execute.
So you need to apply, you need to essentially control the source of this ALU which coming from these
two registers.
So that's why we you're controlling the ALUSRCSRCA&ALUSRCB and the ALU operation also needs to be
defined based on the instruction that you are doing.
And after calculating the result, you need to write it back.
So at the another estate ale you write back, you handle this Reg this mem to Reg and also Reg write.
So with that you can handle R type instructions.
And for for branch if equal essentially you first calculate.
So after fetch this is the fetch.
And in the decode actually here for branch if you call you can actually use this estate to calculate
the branch target address for branch if you call also for branch not equal so you which is good
which this can actually give us some you know the the fact that we have this balance design and we
are trying to utilising our hardware.
So in this state, even though conceptually actually in decoded state, you don't really want to do
operation, you want to decode, right?
But in order to reduce the complexity and in order to in order to avoid adding more resources, you
essentially you can use this state for two different reasons.
1 is that calculating, 1 is decode, another one is.
Is actually also calculating the target memory address, targets branch address.
And yeah, so essentially you calculate the target branch address here and then at this estate you
essentially decide you handle this.
Basically you evaluate the branch whether or not you want to take the branch or not, which is
happening in this estate, which if you look at it is going to be again sourcing the ALU from the
register file and do the operation of subtract because it's a branch.
If you call and use the output of the ALU this 01 in order to see whether or not we want to take the
branch question, OK.
And it's going to be kind of a multi cycle control FSM complete.
They're going to be there are a lot of instructions that I mean, your book also started with subset
of MIPS instructions and control and construct this data pass as well as the control unit.
If you want to, for example, add some other operations like add immediate essentially again, you
can, you know, add different other states.
So if if your current multi cycle FSM cannot support all instructions and you have some instruction
so you don't need to worry you just you just add other states to control it.
And sometimes you need to add basically some more control signals for supporting those instructions.
But it's actually in the sense that this is much more programmable.
You can program your control FSM in order to be able to run different instructions.
So this is for example for AD immediate.
If you want to support jump instruction, for example, our data pass was not enough.
So you can essentially your book also talks about updating the data pass.
So this multiplexer which was selecting previously only for two sources, now it's need to selecting
among three sources which one of the source is actually coming from this for the jump target
address which is in the end is is it's PC +4.
Let me see.
Yeah.
So PC Plus 4 is coming from this line, right?
And then you have this immediate target address which is 20, which is instruction 0 to 25, right.
So this instruction 0 to 25 comes here and you just shifts shifted left by two and then you
concatenate this target 28 bits with the four most significant bits of the PC +4.
And with that you have your PC, your target jump target address and that can go through this.
You know the selector of this multiplexer and can be selected in order to be latched in your program
counter.
So you can update your data pass and with that you also need to basically update your control unit.
Now remember that basically PC source in the past it was only one bit because we had a multiplexer
of two input.
But now that we have 3 inputs, essentially this PCSRC is 2 bits.
So we need to update other states that they were for example on the like they were controlling
PCSRC.
So yeah, so you change that PCSRC here, for example, 00.
And then if the opcode is jump, you just go with the PCSRC 10 and then PC write.
And now you can also support jump address.
So there are also other instructions that you can think of.
You can actually look into it as the as optional homework if you're interested like instruction,
remember about jump register that we discussed a little bit, jump and link, register, jump and link
those instruction.
Also, you can see how we can support in this data pass whether or not we are able to support them.
If not, if, if yes, how we can control it?
And if not, how we can modify the data pass such that we should, then we should be able to control
to support these instructions.
But in the end, it's very programmable and methodical in order to support support for all these
instructions.
Question.
OK.
So yeah, so we more or less actually constructed the multi cycle MIPS micro architecture and this is
actually the single cycle MIPS or micro architecture for a subset of instruction in your.
From your book in chapter 7.0 and also this is the multi cycle mixed micro architecture from your
book in chapter 7.4 which you can also check the book For more information if you're interested.
OK, so one question, what does this design assume about memory?
Yeah, it's kind of a single cycle memory, which in reality that's not the case.
Memory can be actually hundreds of cycles, but in multi cycle actually we can easily handle it.
Remember about.
So essentially if you if you access your memory, so in some state states you need to access the
memory, right?
For example in the fetch or for example in your here for load word and store word, right?
So you're accessing memory.
If your memory is not ready, like your data is not ready, you just stay in that state.
So you can think of, OK, I'm going to just, you know, do this busy waiting until my memory is ready.
So and that essentially is about having this, you know, the kind of a bit memory ready bit is an
input to the control logic that determines the next state.
And you've seen that actually in LC3B in the appendix of your work that we, we had some, some of
these states like here for the fetch, you know, you have this estate that until your memory is not
ready, you state you stay in this state.
Essentially you know, you wait.
So here for memory access, here also for memory access and other memory access.
So there are multiple memory accesses in the execution of instructions.
But in multi cycle design you can easily handle that long latency memory which you can stay in some
of these states.
And that's the beauty of this design.
In single cycle micro architecture, we cannot do anything about it, right.
We always need to wait for the longest memory access instruction, which is like can be hundreds of
cycles.
But here those instructions that they don't need a lot of memory accesses, they can just be faster,
they can go in other way around.
OK, very good.
So for writing to the memory, it depends how much robust you want to be.
Sometimes from the program processor point of view, when you when you're writing to the memory, like
when, when you send the data to the memory, you can think of, OK, I'm done with the write, you
know, and you can continue.
But there are some cases that you really want to make sure that your write is done.
Like think of, think about when you want to have some acknowledgement.
You for example, you're writing for a very important data.
You want to make sure that's done.
But I agree with you in general, loads are much more on the critical path because for load you need
to wait.
But for a store, you can have some, you know, some way to, you know, to work around it.
That's true, But it's not always the case that you can just say that, OK, I'm writing sending the
right to the memory and I'm going to continue others instructions.
There are some cases that you need to be, but it needs more.
Maybe in future lectures we can get to that.
Yeah, very good.
Any other questions?
This one was very good question actually.
OK.
So I want to quickly also discuss this micro programme with multi cycle micro architecture.
This actually is going to be kind of optional for you to check it later.
I'm going to provide also references in in your book in Pat and Patil.
But this is very actually interesting to look into it because most of the modern microprocessor,
they're actually doing this micro programme, multi cycle micro architecture.
So it's very interesting to learn about it.
And the idea is actually very simple.
If I want just want to explain to you why we are designing this control signals, they are the this
control logic.
We are essentially we are programming our micro architecture.
So think about your micro architecture as a.
So basically we have a data pass and there are a lot of.
Control logics and essentially by by controlling logic you are generating control signals and by
setting these control signals step by step or state by state you are actually programming your
datapaths and how you want to do it.
So that actually gives you the concept of programming.
So in micro program multi cycle, you can think of OK, we have a program at the high level which has
instructions, you know, at the programmer view.
And then you can think of OK, at the low level at the hardware, we have micro instructions that
essentially these micro instructions are sequencing through the data pass in order to able us to
execute 1 high level instruction.
So when you know this concept actually, then actually supporting complex instructions are not that
hard.
So for example, you want to have let's say matrix matrix multiplication and you know that this
matrix matrix multiplication is going to be sequence of a lot of instructions, smaller instruction
like addition multiplication and so on and so forth.
So you can actually have them as a micro instructions loaded in some memory which is going to see
that.
And then you can sequence through all these execution of those simple instructions.
You can actually have this sequence of instructions, micro instructions going 1 by 1.
You can do loop in them, you can branch in them, you can do everything and essentially you're
programming your data pass at the low level.
OK.
And that's very actually very exciting topic to go into it.
It's actually coming from this also paper, which I encourage you to check, but I'm not going to
actually cover it in detail.
I'm going to just quickly discuss it and get to the the next topic that we have today.
So in micro program control terminology, control signals associate with the current state.
They are considered they are named as micro instruction.
So all these like think about different FSM that we had and in each in each state we have some sort
of control signals, right?
So you can think of OK, all the control signals that we have in each state is considered as a micro
instruction, OK.
And then act of transitioning from one state to another, which is happening in the FSM here is
determining the next state and the micro instructions for the next state.
Like from 1 micro instruction, we want to go to next micro instructions.
And that is actually considered as micro sequencing.
So this is a terminology that you want to knowing it if you want to get familiar with this topic.
And then you need to have this control store that stores control signals for every possible state.
So essentially I'm going to show you in the picture, it's going to be in in the memory you're going
to store all these control signals like the value of them 101000, don't care, don't care, whatever.
So you have all of them in their memory and one line of it is actually going to be 1 micro
instruction for you.
So you execute this micro instruction and based on that micro instruction, micro sequencing, decide
which going to be the next micro instruction to execute.
And with that going 1 by 1, you should be able to execute your instruction.
So micro sequencer determines which set of control signals will be used in the next clock cycle.
So this actually coming from the high level picture that essentially you have this micro sequencer
and this is a controller store which can be actually very large table.
There are a lot of works that people have tried and actually work on it to compress this controller
store which I'm not going into it, but essentially you need to store all these control signals.
There are ways to reduce the, you know, to reduce the area that you need, but essentially people are
doing that.
And then output of this control is store is going to be your micro instruction which going to be
controlled your data paths in order to execute the instructions that you want to do.
So this is as I said, for your own study, you can check pattern pattern revised Appendix C, which
you can, which have basically discuss this interesting topic.
But I'm going to show something more here about it like what happens in a clock cycle, the control
signals, which is micro instruction for the core in the state they control two things.
One of them is processing the data pass and the other one is generation of control signals, which is
micro instruction for the next cycle.
And that's the, the part that sequencer is actually using micro sequencer is using this micro, the
current micro instruction in order to decide what to do for the next cycle and data pass and micro
sequencer operate concurrently.
And here also we have this question that why not generate control signals for the current cycle
basically in the current cycle like the control signal.
That we need for the current cycle by not generating them at the current cycle which we already also
discussed it.
This can actually lessen the control the clock cycle time.
OK, so this is called the micro programmed controller structure.
There are three components micro instruction, controller store and the micro sequencer.
Micro instruction can be for example all the control signals which can be 26 of them for example,
and help determine the next state can be 9 for example, or many other states depending on your data
pass.
And each micro instruction is stored in a unique location in the controller store which is a special
memory structure.
So there is this unique location which address of the state corresponding to the micro instruction.
So essentially each state in the FSM corresponds to 1 micro instruction and the micro sequencer
determines the address of the next micro instruction, which we already discussed it.
OK, so here also this controller store which I discuss it.
So it's a big large table that essentially you have, you know, all these values for control signals
and some information about what should we do for the for the sequencer.
So after this for example, you know that for the fetch when I do the fetch then I need to decode.
So you can actually have your micro instructions.
But for example in some cases the current micro instructions is currently is handling a branch OK, a
branch instruction.
So based on that micro instructions then whether or not you want to take the branch, you might go to
different micro instruction in this sequencer.
So you can actually jump.
Also, you can branch your micro programmed control and with that you can actually implement loop.
So you can actually think of implementing a low level, you know, code that you can actually have
some loop and do branching in your micro programs.
Is it interesting?
OK, It's very interesting for me at this.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah.
And again, so with this idea, actually a simple datapath can become very powerful because you can
support you.
You have a question?
No.
OK, OK.
And yeah, so you can also check it later if you're interested.
As I said, this topic micro programmed for your own study if you're interested.
I just wanted to give you the high level idea of it.
So this actually bring me back to the power abstraction that the concept of controller store of
micro instruction enables the hardware designer with a new abstraction which is micro programming.
The designer can translate any desired operation to a sequence of micro instructions.
So all the designer needs to provide is the sequence of micro instructions needed to implement the
desired operation and the ability of the control logic to correct the sequence through the micro
instructions like the data pass should be also capable of handling that and any additional data
pass elements and control signals needed.
So the interesting thing is that no need if the operation can be translated into existing control
signals.
So in many, many of you have seen cases that for example, you receive micro program patch, you know,
from companies like Intel or so I don't know if you have done it already sometime.
But essentially as these vendors for at some point they identify some bug on the field, you know
that there are some bugs in executing of some instruction which can cause some security basically
concerns.
So they actually change the micro programmed execution of that instruction and they provide a patch.
And essentially you need to run that patch in some level, for example in BIOS.
And then you change this, the micro programme in the in your CPU.
So that's memory in the CPU which is used for this micro programme is actually programmeable.
You can actually rewrite on it.
I mean, not it's not at the user level most of the time.
In fact, in some cases it's actually the user level, but in.
But it's possible that you can actually do that.
And vendors are using that in order to add instructions on the field, in order to correct some
instructions, execution of some instruction on the field and so on and so forth.
And actually that also again brings us to this semantic gap trade off that we discussed in some
previous lectures that essentially we can have this ISA with complex.
Instructions and data types, types and addressing modes.
And then we can have a low level implementation ISA with simple instruction data types and
addressing modes.
And this is a kind of a hardware translator, which is is exactly our micro sequencer here.
So if you now that you know this topic, you have this is your ISA and this line is actually your
micro instructions and your micro sequencer is actually is in charge in order to translate your ISA
instructions to the sequence of micro instructions that can be executed nicely and negatively on
your hardware.
OK, so now this actually ISA semantic gap makes a lot of sense I guess Question.
OK, so there are a lot of advantages of micro program control.
First of all it allows a very simple design to do powerful computation by controlling the data pass
using the sequencer.
So you can have high level ISA that translated in micro code sequence of instructions.
And this micro code enables A minimal data pass to emulate an ISA.
And also you can think of micro instructions as a user invisible ISA which also consider as UIS so,
so this ISA is not actually visible to the to the user of course.
Also it enables easy extensibility of the ISA.
So we can support a new instruction by changing the micro code and it can support complex
instruction as a sequence of simple micro instructions also enables update of machine behaviour
like a bugging implementation of an instruction can be fixed by changing the micro code in the
field.
So yeah, you're able to update how your machine works like the ability to update and patch micro
code in the field which I already talked about it and you can fix buggy problems.
There are actually historical examples like in IBM 370 model micro code is stored in main memory and
it can be updated after a reboot.
In IBM System Z they call it a mini code in IBNZZ series processor which they have used this
concept.
Also in this machine B 1700 micro code can be updated while the processor is running which is
another level of thinking.
This one is actually user micro programming machine.
So while so like while you're doing programming, like you have a program which is running on your
processor by the same time, you can also try to update your program, right?
But you, you can also think about doing the same thing at the at the processor level, which is you
can update while your processor is running.
You can actually start updating your micro programmed, basically micro programmed table in your
processor at the user level.
So there are a lot of interesting reading here.
If you're interested, you can check For more information and the systems today use microcode patches
to fix hardware bugs and issues, which I discussed about.
If you want to learn more about it, I suggest you'd also check this lecture.
We in the past we we were covering this part actually much more detail.
So you can check some of our previous lectures in Spring 2018 or for example in computer
architecture in 2013 in Carnegie Mellon, actually in the very, very past, OK.
Questo c'è.
Yes.
time vessel?
Yeah.
So that's that's more or less the problem like if you want that low level ISA, if you want to
implement your high level codes with that, it's going to be a hard job for compiler.
And then they cannot really generate, they cannot do easily a lot of optimizations.
The complexity, sorry, like if they are, but that's true that when you have, when you have that
ability, you theoretically you should be able to optimise more.
But the problem is that all these optimisation algorithms, they are actually very complex and time
consuming.
Like there are a lot, some of them, they are not actually, they are not polynomial, right?
So in the end, you are doing a lot of heuristics.
So theoretically, yes, you should be able to optimise more, I agree.
But in reality, it's better to have higher abstraction layer such that you can optimise that bill,
you know, with some ISA and then try to optimise again that level to the lower level.
So think about it that when you want to like, let me give this similar analogy, like when we want to
design data paths, we have a lot of components, right?
So we don't do this, let's say true this true stable for all these Boolean logic for all, everything
we have and then try to simplify the whole data pass together, right?
We don't do that because it's almost impossible, but we do.
We try to have optimised components and try to optimise each component itself and then combine all
these, let's say optimised components to make a bigger data pass.
So yes, what we get the artefact of our design is we cannot say that this is the optimised data pass
that we could get, but this is a kind of a practical design choice that we have made.
Similar stuff is also going going on here with that abstraction.
Yeah.
So when you add translation layer, of course it adds some overhead in between of course, because you
know, you you're playing, you have some overhead of translating and you have less information about
what's going on.
So there are some information hidden to you and that actually limits your capability of optimising
your code.
And that's completely the case.
However, it also provides very good things about it as well.
So in the end, the trade off.
So I agree that we need to have abstraction layers, but we should be careful how many abstraction
layers we are adding to it.
OK.
And sometimes we can actually do have some feedback through it.
It's very similar to just in time compiled, for example, in Java.
Have you have you been programming with Java, for example?
So in just in time actually your your instruction actually high level is translated to some
instruction which can be run with a Java virtual machine.
And that Java virtual machine needs to be translated to a instruction which can be run in your real
hardware.
And that translation actually can be optimised through there in the field.
And then after you get to some optimization, you have it as a just in time compile that you store it
somewhere.
Next time that you want to transition, you don't do the transition again.
You just fetch it from what you have done in the past.
So you can actually optimise with the feedback you are getting in the field in order to optimise it.
So it's, yeah.
So with that feedback, actually you can also overcome some of the limitations of this abstraction
layer, but we can discuss more also later if you're interested.
But very good question because you're thinking quite deep in that line, which which is good.
OK.
So let me start also with this favorite question again.
Can we do better?
And of course we are not able to finish it today and we're going to see a lot more tomorrow, but
it's good to start with the high level idea.
So this is a multi cycle MIPS processor that we design.
And also we discussed that we can easily handle multi cycle memory access in this.
But we know that this in multi cycle design there are some limitation and one of them was that
limited concurrency which we discussed in the beginning that some hardware resources are ideal.
During different phases of instruction processing cycle like fetch logic is idle when an instruction
is being decoded or executed.
So so most of the data path is idle when a memory access is happening.
So there these are these basically the problems of limited concurrence.
So we want to have a higher concurrency in the end in order to provide better performance.
So the the idea, the the key question that we're going to ask here is that can we use the idle
hardware to improve concurrency?
And the goal is to provide more concurrency, which is higher instruction throughput.
So essentially we want to do more work completed, more work completed in one cycle.
So the the idea is that when an instruction using some resources in its processing phase, we can
process other instructions on either resources not needed by by that instruction.
Like 1 when I fetch 1 instruction and then when I get to the decoder stage, so the fetch logic is
now is idle.
So I can use that fetch to fetch logic to fetch another instruction.
And while I'm while I'm executing 1 instruction, I can decode other instruction and that decode when
I'm decoding that instruction, I can also fetch another instruction.
So you can actually apply this idea and this can actually provide much better performance for us
better come currency.
But of course we should be careful.
We're going to get to a lot of issues when we want to do that and it's going to be a lot the topic
of tomorrow how we're going to handle with all these issues.
So in the end, yeah, that's what we discuss about it.
And essentially we want to do different instructions in different steps of pipe in our micro
architecture.
And of course, we need to be more careful than this.
It's not just, you know, basically putting some barriers in your design and then this idea can be
implemented.
You're there are going to be a lot of issues that we're going to solve tomorrow.
So that brings me to this idea of pipelining which the basic idea is actually we want to pipeline
the execution of multiple instructions.
And you can have an analogy of assembly line processing of an instruction like in factories, the
assembly line that they are, they have constructed for example car for automobile assembly line.
You can also think of having the same for instructions.
So we have different steps and the one each instruction is going through all these steps and while
when the previous steps are empty, we can feed another instruction and then we can have it.
And that can provide essentially a lot more throughput.
I'm going to show you a picture which can actually illustrate a very good this idea.
So we divide the instruction processing cycle into distinct stages of processing and we ensure there
are enough hardware resources to process 1 instruction in each stage and we process different
instruction in each stage.
So instructions consecutive in program order or process in the consecutive stages essentially.
And that benefits is actually it provides us higher instruction per cycle which is so essentially.
So your throughput is increasing essentially you are so in your hardware in each cycle because one
cycle your fetch logic is active, your decode logic is active, execute logic is active, right back
is also active, all of them are active and you're actually doing other instruction then.
So essentially in each instruction you're executing multiple instructions.
So that's provide for us higher instruction per cycle, which means that it can the other way around.
The average clock that you spent to execute one instruction, your CPI is going to be lower.
So that's the idea which we want to get to that with concurrency.
But there are a lot of downsides that we're going to see a lot.
And it's good to start thinking about it as well.
You can also think about it, but we're going to see a lot tomorrow.
So with this picture I can actually quickly illustrate like in multi cycle, assuming that we have
this fetch the code, execute and write back.
So in multi cycle we have 4 cycles for instruction.
So you do fetch the code, execute and write back and then you go to the next instruction.
You're essentially serialising the execution of all these instructions.
So if you have 4, let's say these instruction, you're going to have 4 * 4 cycles, which is 16
cycles.
In pipeline the first instruction when you're in decode, you can actually start fetching the the the
next instruction.
And when for example, the first instruction you're in the execute, you can decode in the next
instruction and you can fetching the next instruction.
The next, next instruction, when you're in the right back, you can execute the next instruction, you
can decode the next, next instruction and you can fetch the next, next, next instruction.
And when your pipeline is full, essentially when you're in a steady state in in one cycle,
essentially you are all the steps, stages of the Python are active and that provide actually the
illusion that we have one instruction completed every cycle.
So when your pipeline full every cycle you're going to finish one instruction.
That's a steady state throughput that we're going to get.
So here for this code, because we have only four instructions it it will take some time to you know
to have your pipeline full and then it will also take some time to finish the pipeline.
So it's going to be overall 4567 cycles, which is a very good improvement compared to 16 cycles.
OK.
So here I will stop and I will start from the next slide tomorrow and then going to get to issues of
pipeline.
Have a nice evening.